Hello, and welcome back to another
video with, ItsDrDan, and what we are
going to be looking at today is density.
Specifically, we're going to look
at the properties of matter and then
discuss what is density, which is
a common, uh, conversion factor and
term that we use to describe different
properties and something that we
utilize very often in chemistry.
So before we even talk about
that, let's look at what matter
is so that we can understand where
does this property come from.
So matter just as a basic definition
is anything that, that occupies
a volume and or, or space.
And when that occupies that
space, it also has a mass to it.
So if you think of your computer
or your phone, for example, right,
it can, it has so much space to it.
And you can also put it on
a balance and get its mass.
Um, now, if, how else can
you tell if it has matter?
It's something you can actually
have observations to see it, right?
You can touch it.
You can taste it.
You can smell it.
Feel it.
Because of that, that's
what describes it as matter.
So it's something you can interact with.
Now, whenever we have these different
types of matter, well, they all
have different types of properties
that you can use to describe them.
Um, now, all these different properties,
these are just referred to as
characteristics that you can use to try
to explain the quality of that system.
Now, in science, we usually try to
split those two types of properties.
We like to describe physical properties,
so things that you can actually easily
observe, and chemical properties
that generally help describe how
the actual material behaves if it's
to go through a reaction, like if
something's flammable, for example.
Um, we're going to more specifically
look at the physical properties because
the first thing is, is whenever we have
the different physical properties, they
can be broken down into two categories.
So if you think from before,
we had physical and chemical.
And now these even break
down even farther, right?
Little subcategories.
So the first one is just
essentially anything you can
usually do in the lab, right?
So extensive properties is
something that it changes.
If you add more math, essentially,
you add more matter to it.
So you just keep adding things to it.
That's going to change that property.
So for example, if you, um, have size,
length, volume, mass, weight, width, If
any, all those things can increase if
you add more of whatever the object is.
So the example that I sometimes commonly
use is, let's say if you have a coin
or like a penny, and you just have one
of them, well you just have one coin.
If you have two, three, four, five,
or six, well now you have multiple
of them, and if you were to put them,
let's say, on a balance, The mass
would theoretically double, triple,
quadruple each and every time.
So that's an extensive property
because the more matter you
added, the higher the mass got.
Um, if you were to try to, uh, measure
the length of one penny, right, you would
get You know, maybe a little bit under a
half an inch, you had two of them, you'd
get a whole inch and so forth, right?
It continuously continues to double.
So this is just a normal
measurement, right?
Now an intensive property is
something that you can use
to define a characteristic of
whatever type of matter it is.
Meaning it can be something
that is a little, potentially a
little more unique for that item.
So, for example, maybe the color, right?
So going back to the penny example,
you know it has a copper color.
You have an idea of how
to help identify a penny.
Versus maybe a quarter, right?
That has a more silver
characteristic to it.
Odors are another thing that
could be very unique for different
things that you see every day.
Um, one of the great examples
is think of food, right?
You, how can you tell different foods
is a lot of times by your smell, right?
If you go in the kitchen and
something's being cooked, you
can get an idea of what it is.
Um, other things has to do
with the states of matter.
So solids, liquids, and gases,
and how they can change between
all those different states.
The temperatures of when they change is
going to be different for every single
type of thing that you're looking at.
And then the last thing is the density,
which is what we're going to be looking
at in this video and trying to get an
understanding of, of really what is it.
And then we'll show some,
uh, show a cool video.
really seeing it live in action.
So let's take a look at what is density.
Okay.
So what is density?
What is, what does that exactly mean?
Well, one of the common sayings
we like to say to people is how
dense could you possibly be, right?
It's whenever you're a
little bit hard headed.
Now that comes from the idea
of what density is all about,
uh, an easy ish way to get it.
It has to do with.
How much mass is occupying a given volume?
So one way to look at it is think
of solids, liquids, and gases.
If you think of the containers that I have
above now, if I have a solid, like let's
say a block of metal, for example, if you
were to throw that into water, would the
metal just float on top or would it sink?
And you can think that, right?
It would sink.
Now, why is that?
Well, it has to do with the density.
It has to do with how closely packed
are those little atoms towards each,
uh, right next to each other, right?
So if I have all these little, little
orbs here, you can see they're all
really nice and closely packed together.
So we're fitting a lot of mass in a very,
very tiny area versus let's say a liquid.
Well, okay.
If I have all these little orbs.
You can see that they're a
little bit more spread apart.
They're not as close together.
It's not as thick, right?
So if you have something like water
versus maybe like vegetable oil or
honey, you can kind of see each one
of them has a different viscosity
to it or a different density.
So it's something that it can vary
between liquid, liquid, however,
something like a metal block is
going to sink right to the bottom.
They have different amount of matter
jammed pack in one little vessel, right?
And all these are the same size vessel,
but depending on how much mass or
matter you have jammed in there, it's
going to have a different density.
And the last one's a gas, right?
When you have gas particles like
what you're breathing right now,
you're breathing oxygen and nitrogen.
All those gas particles are
free flowing all around you.
Now, there's trillions upon trillions
of atoms that are very far spread
apart around you, and they're not
so close, densely packed together
that you can easily see it, right?
Now, what is a way for
you to maybe see it?
Well, let's say if it gets,
think of water vapor, right?
So water can either be
solid, liquid, or gas.
Well, if it's very, very cold outside
and it starts getting very, very foggy,
that's when that water vapor starts
to condense a little bit thicker and
thicker, so it's a little denser.
versus when it's a nice hot day, you
can see it's more spread out and it
feels a little bit more muggy and humid.
So, the entire definition of density is,
it's the amount of mass per unit volume.
So what we're actually going to be
doing is combining units together,
because we're interested in how
much mass occupies a given space.
Now, why is that so important?
Well, this is where, this is one of
the intrinsic properties of matter.
So if I had, let's say, a very, an
example I like to use in my classes
here, I have lead beads on the
left, and then I have a pool noodle.
And if I ask you, which one
do you think is more dense?
So something what it means by
more dense means that there's
more mass in a given volume.
Now notice how they're both
completely different sizes.
And one of these, you know,
for a fact floats, right?
You've probably had a pool noodle
at some point in your life.
You've been around a pool, it
floats now, but it's massive.
So does this have a higher
or less density than lead?
And you can probably think, well, lead's
a metal, it's going to sink right away.
So that's going to have a higher.
density.
And that's because there are more
atoms jam packed into one small
area that can be easily measured.
So within that five millimeters of
space, there are more atoms jammed
together and that's a unique value
for lead versus something that's more
of like a styrofoam that's going to
have its own unique value for it.
So what we're going to look at next is
being that we do have that intrinsic
property of That's available to us.
It's different for every material.
We can use it as a method
to identify things.
All right.
So what we have here is
a video from Dave hacks.
com, which he's on YouTube and he
made a density demonstration here.
Uh, so what he's doing is he has a glass
of water and you put water in there.
He's going to be adding food dye to it.
So water has a density of
one gram per milliliter.
So this is usually what we use
as a metric to determine will
something float, will it sink?
So.
Usually metal will, will sink
down to the bottom of the glass.
Something that's very, very, uh,
low density will float on the top.
So he'll have those mixed up so you
can always see that water layer.
He'll mix it up.
Now what he's pouring in there
is this, uh, honey liquid.
And what you can see immediately is
that it sank right down to the bottom.
So what does that exactly mean?
Well, that tells you that
this has a higher density.
As a result, so if it sinks,
it has a higher density.
So greater than one,
uh, is what that means.
So it sank right away.
So now when you, when you pour in
a little bit more water, you'll
see that, oh, the water didn't sink
below the, into the honey layer.
It's still added to the blue layer.
It didn't do anything.
Now, when he adds oil on top,
which is very similar to like
making a salad dressing, which
is that oil and vinegar layer.
Vinegar is very similar to
water, is a very similar density.
The oil goes to the top and
then the water is on the bottom.
So that tells you oil has an
even lower density than water.
So oil floats, let's say it could
be like maybe around like 0.
7 grams per milliliter.
Water's around 1 and then
maybe the honey is around 1.
3 for example.
So you can kind of see
that, that layering effect.
Now, even when it can, uh, you could have
like all kinds of different effects here.
Uh, so one of the things he's
going to do here in a second
is drop different objects in.
So you can see he drops a bolt in
and it sinks right to the bottom.
And that makes sense, right?
Metal sinks.
That's like our lead beads
that I showed earlier.
Anything that's metal
has a very high density.
It's usually greater than.
Typically, most metals are greater
than seven grams per milliliter,
except for maybe aluminum, which is
a little bit lower, but it's very,
very heavy or very, very dense.
Um, versus let's say he puts a grape
in, well, a grape is a piece of fruit.
Well, let's see what happens
here when he puts that in there.
It sinks right through the oil, right
to the bottom of water, which makes
sense, but notice how it floats.
right on top of the honey.
It doesn't go any farther.
So the, what does that tell you?
So the metal has a higher
density than everything.
Then the grape has a higher density
than water, but it's lower than honey.
Now on the next one, what
is he going to add in now?
He has a plastic bottle cap.
He puts that in and you can see it's
going to float right on the top of water.
So it's like having like
that trash layer float.
And then you have a piece of
styrofoam that floats on top.
So all these densities are different.
So it's like a ranking of density, right?
So lowest is all the way on the top.
And then the highest is on the bottom.
So that's density at work.
And you can do any of this at
home with household chemicals
and stuff that's laying around.
As I mentioned, density is a permanent
characteristic of any substance.
So if I have any liquid or any
solid, they're all going to have
their unique density values.
We can use that to determine
whether or not something is a
very specific characteristic.
There's methods that we can use to try
to figure out what is it that we have.
So for example, let's say if I had water,
ethanol, methanol, and benzene, and I were
to dump, let's say, the water and benzene
into this beaker here, what would happen?
Well, think about it.
Which one is a higher density?
Well, water has the biggest value.
So if I were to pour water into
the speaker, it would end up
sinking to the bottom, right?
Just like in the video, it would
have been that this one would
actually have a higher density.
Now, if instead, let's say if I
had a benzene, where would that go?
Well, being that it has a 0.
876 grams per milliliter value, it
would end up floating on the top.
So you would see a layer
of benzene on the top.
And being that these two are not
soluble with one another, you would
see them end up separating as a
result, just like in the video.
So this gives us an idea of what
type of different properties we
might have, but depending on what
it is that you're looking at.
So let's take a look at some examples.
How could we actually apply
this in the classroom?
So, suppose you forgot to label the
following beakers, you have three
beakers, each one of them has 230
milliliters of a clear liquid in them.
How would you determine which one
is water, ethanol, and benzene?
How could we try to go about through that?
Well, let's try to think about it.
What exactly is density?
Let's take a look at some tips and try
to understand what it is that we have.
Thinking of density as a formula.
meaning that density is
equal to mass over volume.
So whenever we have a density,
typically we end up showing this at
putting a d here as the letter to use.
It's generally the not capitalized
version, which is equal to density, and
that is going to be mass over volume.
Now this is more commonly referred to as
grams over ml whenever we are using it,
and we can treat it just like a formula.
So if you were trying to go back to
our last problem, and we were trying to
figure out, well, which one do we have?
Well, we could try something,
simple characteristics, right?
We know the volumes of
the three beakers, right?
All the liquids were 230 mls.
So we already have the vol, the value
for this bottom, uh, piece that is here.
So how could we end up trying
to figure out the other?
Well, we need the mass.
Well, what do you have
available to you in the lab?
Is there anything you can use?
And you'll quickly remember,
oh, we have balances.
So what if you just weigh the
different liquids that you have?
Why not?
Right?
You can put the beaker on the
balance, weigh it and determine
exactly how much that liquid weighs.
So let's go back to that example.
So let's say if I weigh
the first one, right?
And you determine that
it weighs 202 grams.
So what we could do is,
okay, I have 202 grams.
I could divide that by 230.
ML, and what would you end
up getting for your value?
You would quickly see
that you would get 0.
878 grams for every one milliliter, right?
If we simplify that fraction.
So using your calculator, so if you just
do 202 divided by 230, you'll get 0.
878.
So, which one is it?
So if we go back to our
chart from earlier, 878 is
very, very close to benzene.
So we can see that this one is 876.
They're about the same.
So let's say that the
very first one is benzene.
And that's just one way to do it.
You could get the odor possibly, maybe
do some other different chemical tests.
This is an easy one that's
available to you at your own home.
Okay, so what about the second one?
Let's say if I do the same idea, I
measure the weight of that one too.
So we get 229 grams, I divide
that by 230 mLs, and when we get
our final number, we'll get 0.
996 grams per milliliter.
And we can see that, oh, well, 0.
996, that's very, very close to water.
So that means that our second
one is going to be H2O.
Now, is this the only way you can do it?
Well, let's take a look at another tip
in order to figure out the third way.
Alright, so there's another
method to solving for these.
Last way to think about density.
So the first way was to
think of it as a formula.
The second way is to use
it as a conversion factor.
This is one of the few conversion
terms that you have that allows
you to go from mass to volume.
It's a bridge.
It allows you to convert from
one type of unit to another.
It allows you to derive new values
based on things you can find in the lab.
So, if I, let's say I have water, right,
which is one gram per mL is its density.
We can write this as a conversion term by
saying that, okay, one gram is equivalent
to one milliliter, like a fraction, or
we could flip it to use it for however
you want to cancel out units, right?
So if I had one ml, you could also say
that's equal to one gram for water.
Now, what exactly do I mean by that?
Well, think of the example
that we were just doing.
Well, earlier, we had two hundred
and thirty So, if I were to take,
let's say, one of the densities, and
we'll use the, we'll use the density
of methanol, which was one of the
other ones that was in that table.
So if I want to cancel out my units,
how would you end up trying to do that?
Well, the density of
methanol was 792 grams.
Over one milliliter.
So what would I put on the
bottom here to cancel it out?
Well, milliliter needs to
be opposite of milliliter.
For them to cancel, right?
Units need to cancel.
This would leave you with 0.
792 grams on top.
This would give you grams.
So once you go through the math for
that, you should have 182 grams.
So if you were to measure any of
those beakers and if any of them
equaled 182 grams, that means that
you, that you have your answer.
So let's go take a look
if we got it correct.
If I go back up to my three beakers,
it's the last one, 182 grams.
It is for planning purposes, but you
could have did that in the very beginning.
You could have calculated.
What any of your values are,
and then solve that way as well.
There's multiple ways
for you to use density.
Don't forget it because it's going
to be a very useful term for when
you get to dimensional analysis and
stoichiometry and solution chemistry.
Density is very, very handy.
Let's go look at another problem.
Density.
What is the volume in liters of air?
the mass is 100 grams with a density of 0.
001184.
Grams per milliliter.
Okay.
So if we were to do this problem,
first thing we always want to do
is we want to write down what our
desired and our given terms are
to help keep ourselves organized.
So the first thing, what
do we actually want?
We want volume and we want it in liters.
So we're going to write that down.
Now, what else were we
given in the problem?
Well, if we take a look,
we have a mass here.
that we can write down.
So let's do that.
So which is a hundred grams.
And then we also have a density
which is available to us too.
So we will put that down as well, right?
We have this density.
So that value is 0.
00184 or sorry, 1184 grams
for every milliliter.
And we could also have the
flipped version as well.
So I like to write down all possibilities
so that way we can see, okay, how can all
these little pieces plug together because
unit conversions can only fit one way.
All right.
So based on these terms, which one
would make more sense to start with?
What we have is we have
a conversion factor.
on the bottom, and then we have a
term that's by itself on top, a.
k.
a.
your mass.
So which one do you want?
Now with the term by itself, there's no
way for you to flip this fraction wise.
Not, at least not in a
way that would make sense.
So if we start with the 100 grams,
What we can do is we can put
that on top of our t table and
then allow our units to guide us.
So from here, we want to
be able to cancel grams.
So where, which one of these terms
would have grams on the bottom?
And what you'll see really quickly
is this guy down over here, right,
has grams already on the bottom.
So we're going to use
that to cancel our units.
So we'll put 0.
00 1184 frames on bottom, 1 ml on top.
That will get us to volume.
Now, keep in mind, we have to get
this to liters, so how can we do that?
Well, using conversion sheets, you will
see that 1000 milliliters is 1 liter.
And we can double check,
did our units cancel?
We'll see grams cancelled grams, and
then milliliters cancelled milliliters,
and we're in our final unit.
Once we do that, what can we, we want
to make sure that we put our value
down here, which we will get 84.
5 liters as our final answer,
and we round it to three sig
figs because we had 100 grams.
So this would be your final answer.
So in this case, we use
density as a conversion factor.
Whereas before we used it both as
a formula and a conversion factor.
This is the more common way, is
that using as a conversion term.
I hope this video helped.
I know it was a little longer,
but it's something that density is
used so much in general chemistry
and in first year chemistry.
I hope it helped, and I hope to
see you all again in the future.
And thank you all so much for listening.
I hope you guys have a wonderful day.
Bye now.